A Guide to the Papers of Louis I. Jaffé, 1918-1954
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Louis I. Jaffé 1918-1954
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9924-f
672 items (2 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This addition to the Jaffé collection was given to the Library by Mrs. Louis I. Jaffé, on April 13, 1979.
Biographical/Historical Information
Louis I. Jaffé was born in Detroit, Michigan, February 22, 1888, the son of Phillip and Lotta Maria (Kahn) Jaffé. When Jaffé was twelve years old, his family moved to Durham, North Carolina, and he graduated from high school there in 1907. In 1911, he received an A.B. degree from Trinity College (now Duke University).
While a student at Trinity, Jaffé edited The Chronicle, a campus weekly, and was associate editor of The Archive, a college monthly. After graduation, he joined the staff of the Durham Sun, but left a short time later to become a reporter and assistant city editor for the Richmond Times- Dispatch.
In 1917, Jaffé was commissioned as Second Lieutenant in the Field Artillery Section, Officer's Reserve Corps of the United States Army. He was re-commissioned in the Aviation Section 1918, and again in 1919 with the Service of Supply. He was honorably discharged in France, March 29, 1919, and was commissioned as Inspector in the American National Red Cross with rank of Captain. He served on the Red Cross Commission to the Balkans from April to July, 1919, and was director of the Red Cross News Service in Paris from July to October, 1919. He was made a Chevalier of the State of Roumania, and honor bestowed in recognition of his work there with the Red Cross Commission.
After the war, Jaffé went to Norfolk to become editor of the Virginian-Pilot, a position he held from 1919 until his death in 1950. He was prominent among Virginia liberal journalists and won the Pulitzer Prize in 1929 for an editorial deploring a lynching which took place in Houston, Texas, on the eve of the Democratic National Convention.
In one of his last editorials, dated February 25, 1950, concerning the "mercy killing" of the Boothe bill for desegregation of Virginia public transportation he wrote: "The Virginia Democratic organization makes haste slowly in the field of social-political reform...It is still too uneasy about the impact of de-segregation on common carries to give the proposal anything like an official blessing. That will come later-after a longer look at this highly desirable reform, and possibly after another shove or two from the Supreme Court of the United States."
Scope and Content
This addition to the Louis I. Jaffé papers consists of 672 items (2 boxes), Jaffé's correspondence files "M-N" from the years 1918 to 1954. Correspondents include Ralph McGill, Archibald MacLeish, Don Marquis, Robert Douthat Meade, R. Walton Moore, Francis Pickens Miller, Edwin Mims, and Henry M. Morganthau, Jr. The other correspondents are chiefly personal friends, political figures, professional associates, and people with whom Jaffé was involved in relation to his various civic activities. There is material relating to the Norfolk City Tax Commission, of which Jaffé was secretary; the Norfolk Division of William and Mary; the Norfolk Museum of Arts and Sciences; and the Norfolk Unit of the Virginia Union University (now Norfolk State University). General topics discussed in the correspondence include journalism, politics, literature, education, and Norfolk news and institutions.
Arrangement
The correspondence is arranged alphabetically. There is a general folder for each letter of the alphabet followed by individual folders for more prominent correspondents. Each correspondent's letters are further arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- "M" through "McN" 1920-1950, 47 items (Box 1)
- "Mea" through "Mye" 1922-1948, 45 items (Box 1)
- Mackreth, A.R.W. ( Literary Digest ) 1920-1925, 9 items (Box 1)
- MacLeish, Archibald 1942, 1 item (Box 1)
- Mallon, Paul 1944, 1 item (Box 1)
- Mann, James 1923-1944, 8 items (Box 1)
- Maphis, Charles G. (UVA Institute of Public Affairs) 1929, 5 items (Box 1)
- Mapp, J. Walker 1925-1941, 12 items (Box 1)
- Marquis, Don 1934, 2 items (Box 1)
- Marr, Janey Hope 1932, 7 items (Box 1)
- "Matt" 1918-1920, 6 items (Box 1)
- Matton, George 1934-1949, 6 items (Box 1)
- Maupin, William G. 1928-1949, 5 items (Box 1)
- McCordell, Lee A. 1923, 8 items (Box 1)
- McClean, Robert 1923, 19 items (Box 1)
- McClure Newspaper Syndicate 1920-1924, 8 items (Box 1)
- McCormick, Virginia Taylor 1923-1941, n.d., 20 items (Box 1)
- McKissick, Judge Rion 1920-1936, 6 items (Box 1)
- McLemore, James S. 1930-1944, 6 items (Box 1)
- McNaught's Monthly 1925-1926, 10 items (Box 1)
- McPherson, Holt 1949, 3 items (Box 1)
- Meechan, William Shands 1927-1948, 63 items (Box 1)
- Meade, Robert Douthat 1941-1946, 12 items (Box 2)
- Miles, John B. 1920-1936, 17 items (Box 2)
- Miller, Francis Pickens 1940-1948, 13 items (Box 2)
- Mims, Edwin 1926-1928, 11 items (Box 2)
- Montgomery, Walter A. 1924-1932, 10 items (Box 2)
- Moore, R. Walton 1925-1938, 36 items (Box 2)
- Mordecai, Samuel F. 1925-1926, 3 items (Box 2)
- Morganthau, Henry, Jr. 1945, 1 item (Box 2)
- Moreland, John Richard 1927-1944, n.d., 19 items (Box 2)
- Morely, Felix 1933-1944, 13 items (Box 2)
- Morris, Major C.D. 1919-1926, 12 items (Box 2)
- Murray, K. Foster 1922-1937, 33 items (Box 2)
- Myers, Barton 1921-1926, 6 items (Box 2)
- "N" 1920-1946, 54 items (Box 2)
- Navy 1919-1949, 49 items (Box 2)
- Negro Bathing Beach 1930-1935, 6 items (Box 2)
- Norfolk City Tax Commission: Correspondence 1929, 7 items (Box 2)
- Norfolk City Tax Commission: Resumes of meetings 1929, 11 items (Box 2)
- Norfolk Division of William and Mary 1941, 8 items (Box 2)
- Norfolk Museum of Arts and Sciences ca. 1933-1954, 19 items (Box 2)
- Norfolk Unit: Virginia Union University (now Norfolk State College) 1941-1944, 5 items (Box 2)
- Nottingham, Cherry 1927-1942, 31 items (Box 2)